welcome to
meditative john rovinki we live stream
every weekday morning at 9 30 eastern
time
with mondays we introduce a new lesson
and that's called dominates
and then that alternates on the next
monday with a review of the ecology of
practices
called upaya day and
that is also itself alternates between
uh reviewing the eastern traditions uh
reviewing the practice system we draw
from the eastern traditions
and then reviewing the practices to be
dropping the western traditions this
week is a special week though because
we're doing dharma day on monday
wednesday and friday
in general right now uh monday wednesday
and friday classes will tend to be
longer
if you're joining us for the first time
don't be put off by this odd setup
uh whiteboard etc you're most welcome i
recommend you keep meeting but go to the
description and then there you'll find
links to previous lessons and says do
lesson one right away
and try to do one or two lessons every
week keep meeting with us and eventually
you will integrate into the course
and hopefully also into the community
the cena that's great around it
as i mentioned mondays alternate between
a dharma day
and the uk day and last monday was a day
we're going to pick up on that and have
another dharma day
today some things you can do to help me
is to like this stream
so that i can help as many as people as
possible by liking it you'll raise its
profile on the youtube algorithm
and to help the outreach um
at the end of every session uh we sit
and then after that we have q a please
limit your questions
to anything from the entire ecology
practices
we give priority because it's material
we're working on right now
on monday wednesdays and fridays two
questions from the western ecology of
practice
and tuesdays and thursdays we get
priority to the eastern ecology of
practices
i'm mentioning thursday tomorrow's
thursday and i will not be able to be
here tomorrow
so there is no class tomorrow on
thursday i recommend strongly that you
guys meet
on the discord server and have your
regular uh safe
um i think that's everything we need to
do right now
so let's let's begin
so a quick review we're taking a look at
the second major uh pillar of
vegetarianism we've looked at
the disciplining of desire um arthur
has actually written a book on all these
hellenistic practices called the therapy
of desire
um and in there we looked about you know
discipline your desires so you can
prioritize
and hone in on anorexia the two kinds of
anorexia
and savoring as a practice to give up to
put us in touch
with peritelic anorexia which is uh
the touchstone well now
we're going to look at the disciplining
of
fear so desires oriented towards
pleasure fear oriented towards pain
they are actually interdefining but this
is at least pedagogically useful to make
these distinctions
i want to remind everybody that i agree
wholeheartedly with mclennan
uh that epicureanism is not sufficient
but it is powerful
it is our primary school stoicism will
be our high school
and neoplatonism will be our university
all right
so we're talking about a specific kind
of fear here we're not talking about the
automatic instinctive fear that's
hardwired there's nothing we can do
about that and therefore there's nothing
we should try to do about that
um what we're talking about is the kind
of fear
that results from the way in which we um
self-terrify and that is the way in
which our undisciplined imagination
uh terrifies us and then the idea here
is we want to
create a practice of the reflective
discernment
and disciplining of imagination so
whenever you're getting into an
imaginative state
that is generating fear you're supposed
to bring these epicurean practices
to bear and the mainly the main
set of practices is captured by the
maxim of the four-fold
uh you know don't fear the gods right
don't fear death
don't fear uh you know the loss of pain
and remember that pleasure is easy to
obtain and there's various translations
of it that's the basic idea
okay so we talked about what do we mean
by imagination
we mean that we modern cognitive science
is really moving towards is this idea
that imagination and perception are
interlocking
reception is the bottom-up intake of
new information and then right their
imagination is
is the top-down aspect which is the
prediction of the patterns that are
going to be found
and we can run this top-down prediction
uh without any bottom-up corrective
um information and that's imagination
and the thing about imagination is of
course it opens up the
space of possibilities that we can
consider and that's wonderful
uh but we want to steer a course between
the calvinists who
are afraid of that opening up of the
potential for idolatry
and the romantics who just celebrate it
and don't worry about
the self-deception and so we want
we want a discipline
sorry don't know what that was we
want a a disciplined imagination
so i don't quite know what's going on
right now
so jason's just taking care of it sorry
about that it's not it's now solved
all right so we want a reflectively
disciplined imagination
and what does that mean for us well what
it means is we
note that because imagination does not
have the bottom-up perception
it is especially prey
to cognitive bias and to and therefore
to self-deception
but that doesn't mean we should reject
it or repress it
we should discipline it and use it
properly in a
rationally reflective manner all right
so
the first one is the gods are not to be
feared for many of us
myself included uh we don't believe in
gods
um i'm not not being insulting that's
just a statistical statement
um for those of us who do believe in
some kind of divinity we've had two
millennia of christianity or
islam or judaism teaching us that god is
basically good
and not capricious or malicious but an
inherently moral being
so the actual revolution and the acts of
religions are taking care of sort of
that aspect and i think in that sense
what epicurus was
addressing is obsolete but there is a
way we can expand epicureanism
and make it relevant to us today i'm
going a little bit rapidly because this
is review i'll slow down when we get to
the new
new material one is the uh
and margaret visser makes an excellent
case for this in her book beyond fate
um you can you can see this as the fear
of fate
uh the fear of the fact that uh the
universe unfolds
according to powers and principles
beyond our control beyond our ken
um and in ways that are often completely
indifferent
in a titanic fashion to our narrative
projects our personal concerns
um our relationships etc so that's
uh the idea of fate and then
what is at the core of this is the
understanding often implicit that we are
finite infallible creatures
and that we are always finite infallible
creatures and this is the fatality of
all things
fatality doesn't just mean subject to
death it means
subject to fate not as some you know
pre-written destiny or something like
that
but in the sense that we will always
be finite and fallible and we will
always be vulnerable to be overwhelmed
by forces beyond our understanding and
control and that is
scary no doubt about it and so
learning to not avoid our mortality
but embrace it appropriately is part of
what the epicureans
are trying to give us i think we're
going to need help from the stoics and
the neoplatons down the road
uh so what they um
what they're basically trying to get us
uh to realize
is that um and again the epicurean is
more enacted than actually theorize it
but although we are finite infallible we
are also capable of significant
self-transcendence
we can self-transcend and philosophy is
the practice the art of such
self-transcendence
and so learning to practice philosophy
um
will actually help us like i say there's
been
the point i'm going to make now is going
to be first explicated and then i think
really develop richly
in the neoplatonus that our sense of
coming into contact with which what with
that which that is most real is the
best way to ameliorate
uh our our affinity and our fall ability
so when we kind of when we come into
contact and we can favor
what is most real that addresses um the
concern
that is born in us um from the
confrontation with our mortality
i would put to you that perhaps this at
least what some traditions
uh claim and i have found it to be quite
experientially powerful in my life
that i do not long for immortality
i long for reality along for being most
real
and once that and the stoics claimed and
the new plaintiff's plane that once
you've touched that and this seems to be
central also i would claim buddhism that
once you touch that
um your fear up due to your
mortality diminishes significantly
so the other one might be a fear of the
afterlife um
and like epicurus i use the best science
of our time
i find um and i think this is what the
epicureans would argue i find the
proposal
of an afterlife scientifically
improbable highly improbable
the increasing evidence of the deep
interdependence between
mind brain body and environment and we
clearly know that the body and the brain
perish and are impermanent um
that to me means i i'm not really
concerned with an afterlife but some of
you might have
uh sort of remember i don't use this
word insultingly you might have a mythic
model of the afterlife the epicureans
recommend that you actually imagine that
and and this is where the eastern
traditions can be very helpful
the intro traditions ask you to re
actually expand your imagination
and confront the horror of immortality
uh that living forever would is
basically an attempt to freeze the world
and to freeze yourself
and this is just titanically would empty
everything of meaning you face a
meaningless existence
this is why uh that in vedanta you see
muksha which is release
from immortality or in buddhism nirvana
the blowing out of the flame of personal
immortality
etc so i think if you open yourself
up to both the science and alternative
mythologies that have a much more
expansive imagination
that can significantly ameliorate the
fear of the afterlife
so then we moved into what we're
actually confronting when we confront
the fear of mortality is the fear of
death
and then the epicureans
point out that well there's two aspects
this one is the fear of
so here's the mortality
and what you might be fearing here is
death
uh or if you're dying
and then they point out again using
imagination in a disciplined
rational fashion um that
if your fear of death is the fear of
non-existence that's absurd
uh there has been eons and eons when you
did not exist
and that doesn't strike you with terror
or it shouldn't strike you with terror
um and you can't actually experience
your non-existence
i'll be curious they said where death is
i am not
where i am death is not so you're
fearing something that you will never
experience you will never know so
those two you know if you actually play
with your imagination in those two ways
in a rationally disciplined fashion it's
like oh right non-existence isn't
something that i should fear
now but something that i don't think the
epicureans quite got is some people
you know it's yeah but it's actually
that mysteriousness of fear
not it's theoretical there's no
theoretical mystery i know i'm going to
die right
all other creatures do all other things
are impermanent so not
but what we mean by a mystery is it's an
experiential what's called a
phenomenological mystery i cannot
imagine being dead i could imagine
myself in the darkness but
i'm there right and so there's something
inherently mysterious about that and
the fact that we can't imagine it is we
can be very
fearful peer producing in us because we
can't imagine something
that mystery can be oh it's
unpredictable it's uncertain but
technically it's not unpredictable or
uncertain
it's mysterious and then i would
recommend to you that especially in
neoplatonism
what we need to do is to learn to
transform our the aspect of the
mysterious to go from experiencing it
as a primarily negative thing to
experiencing it as a primarily positive
thing and so a kind of experience that
you've all had
that points that out is the experience
of ah strangely the experience of ah we
know this experimentally in
designing experiments with jennifer
steller and michelle uh
ferrari and some cameron doing uh
talking to brian ostof on his
experiences
we know that ah actually diminishes the
sense of self people feel
like they're almost overwhelmed and it's
mysterious
but yet awe is a very positive
experience
it's a very positive experience and
um and what that means is
if we develop a virtue for
awe reverence then we
can train ourselves to confront
mystery in its positive aspect
rather than uh fixating on its negative
aspect
okay so what about the fear of dying
okay and that is something you can
experience and it's
and you know it's kind of unknown um
interestingly enough
um when you get when people actually
sit down this is some of the work done
on death reflection
and they imagine dying and they imagine
their friends with them
this is interesting so when they just
imagine death in the abstract
this that it often and there's some
dispute around this
this research but mortality salience
they sort of get rigid and afraid
but when they go into a first person
perspective and actually imagine dying
with people around them it actually has
the opposite effect it makes them open
compassionate that's interesting
that's interesting because you think
about the
epicurean practice of getting into the
habit
of being in philosophical contemplative
companionship with others
being able to carry that all the way
through that actually hooks up with some
recent empirical data
so again imagine properly imagine
more deeply imagine in a way that is
backed
by whatever whatever scientific evidence
we have
let's take a look at some more of the
that
evidence well what you said well what
i'm afraid is i'm afraid of losing as i
get old i'm going to lose so much
now that's interesting because if you
actually take a look at
a couple things if you look at uh you
know how people's sense of subjective
well-being
how much they sort of like their life um
it has a weird the breath is weird so
this is sort of how much you like your
life and this is your age
like when you're in your 30s and your
40s probably where you are right now it
goes down
so right like so here's you know
childhood into adolescence but what's
what people don't know
and what they expect reasonably is they
expect this
that's what they predict it's reasonable
it's reasonable that's what they imagine
but what they're doing shows is actually
this as people move into their old age
they go up like that
they look like that
hey no these like everything in
psychology
this is probabilistic of course there's
individuals that do this
right but what we're saying is the
prediction of the inevitability of this
is definitely disconfirmed empirical
evidence doesn't support this and you
might ask
well what is going on here people are
losing all very very many pleasures
what is it that's happening here well
what's it seems to be is wisdom now it's
not
it's not necessary that older people are
wiser
that's not an inevitability either but
in general they tend to be
and that seems to be very very
predictive of life satisfaction
and of meaning in life so what's going
up here is meaning in life
and that actually makes life very good
i'm looking for my eraser
i don't know where it is
sorry i can't find it i'm just gonna get
a paper towel
jason's pointed to me but i can't find
it so we'll just use a paper towel
okay so this brings up an interesting
thing and i've mentioned this
and this is the difference between
subjective well-being
your sort of sense of contentment and
meaning in life
and then there's some confusions about
this so
this is your sense of this is the sense
that yourself is sort of satisfied
and solidified and and it's doing well
right and that's a subjective well-being
now interestingly people right
think that power and wealth are the main
route to that and our culture teaches
this and we mention this
with eric trum and what so this is
subjective well-being
and then this is this is wealth or power
because they're often conjoined and what
you find
is right when people are in poverty
their subjective well-being is very low
so we have an obligation to get people
out of poverty out of scarcity
overwhelming evidence but what happened
so
initially differences in wealth make a
huge difference in subjective well-being
and that's where where we get this idea
from
but what happens is then it plateaus and
goes up very very gradually
so that there's only a very small
increase in subjective well-being
with massive increases in wealth
so once you're out of poverty the
pursuit of wealth is an irrational way
to pursue subjective well-being okay so
that's one thing
and then what you have to ask is well
what actually is contributing to
subjective well-being
it has to do more with your sense of
autonomy
and that how much you're how much you're
in control of yourself
and that's what we're learning here with
epicureanism um
your sense of confidence that you have
cultivated skills and virtues
that help you to deal with life and
connectedness
um which actually will you know
relationships to others
but that's a bit where i can i agree
with some people that's where this
construct and this construct to be
confounded
now what's interesting is that how
meaningful people find their lives
is not to be identified with subjective
well-being
because one can go significantly down
and while the other goes up what are two
instances in which
that's the case well one clear instance
is having a child
when you have a child your subjective
well-being crashes you're hungry you're
tired
uh there's a lot of unknowns uh your
finances
are going to be challenged your most
significant relationships are going to
be put up
you know under stress et cetera right so
why do people have children they have
trouble because
meaning in life goes up
when people are getting older aspects of
this go down because your health
declines
your social relationships strength
meaning in life goes
up in life
meaning in life is how you are connected
to yourself
connected to others and connected to
what's most real
so the cultivation of wisdom which is
about removing self-deceptive patterns
that destroy your relationship to
yourself
to other people and to the world is how
you enhance
meaning in life
so and how do we cultivate
wisdom in a way that's going to enhance
meaning in life
by phyllis what the what the epicureans
say is by philosophical contemplative
companionship
by cultivating philosophic shared
philosophy
the shared philosophy of the shared
cultivation of wisdom
with others philia means communal
brotherly like sexist but the communal
love
by leah sophia of wisdom the communal
love of wisdom so
you say well really yeah it's because
what you have to understand is you're
not actually very good at predicting
your subjective
even your subjective wellbeing there's a
thing called the hedonic treadmill
so you can study what happens to people
after they've confronted a significant
now again
probabilistically there are always
individual cases
right but probabilistically you can
study what happens to people who win the
lottery
or who suffer a major accident trauma
and what you find it when it initially
happens there's a huge
change in their subjective well-being
life is great
or life is hell heaven or hell but
within about eight
weeks they return back to the state they
were in
before the lottery and you say it won't
be for me that won't happen for me
oh yeah it will i can make that
prediction with a lot of confidence
or after trauma they return back to
where they were
so your your hedonic set point is
you know it's really really robust and
it
that means environmental changes don't
impact it as much as you can
where you can make a significant
difference
to your happiness if what we mean by
happiness is subjective well-being
plus meaning in life is in your meaning
in life that's where you have the most
control
people are actually really bad at
predicting affect
effective forecasting
this is ask people to imagine how they
will feel in a situation
imagine how you imagine how you'll feel
in a situation
negative or positive and they'll say oh
i'll feel this way or feel bad that way
and then compare that to how they feel
when they actually are in that situation
and they're often dramatically wrong
and you say i don't believe it i'm sorry
i know you don't
that's because your memory is
reconstructive your memory only
pays attention to things that are right
sort of predictively verified for you
you have a confirmation bias so remember
what i said
when you're in the realm of imagination
all the cognitive biases
run riot what does this tell tell us
it tells us that all our imaginings
about dying
are highly probably wrong
all of our imaginings about getting old
are highly
probably wrong
but i can still imagine it of course you
can and you can imagine yourself being
eaten by a dragon
while being stabbed by leprechauns and
that's a horrible amount and it can
provoke you and arouse you
it doesn't mean it's a something that
you should take seriously
do not remember what we said from the
beginning do not confuse the intensity
of your imagining
with the legit religion with the
legitimacy of what it is claiming
those aren't the same thing remember
we're learning to
instead of mistake intensity with
importance
train ourselves to make the important
more intense
that's what we're doing with
epicureanism
so
what does all this mean the epicureans
say well th
this if we need non-existence is absurd
and we can really buttress what the
epicureans did
with this saying well we are confused
uh about a lot of things about
power and wealth subjective well-being
meaning in life
we're confused about how variable they
are do you know that people have the end
of history illusion
this goes into the old age idea too if
you ask people
how much did you change in the last 10
years
it will say a lot how much will you
change in the next 10 years
not at all or very little
and of course every 10 years this
prediction is false
and every 10 years they say oh that past
10 years
i changed a lot and our self-knowledge
isn't as great as we believe it is
so what i'm trying to show you over and
over again
is that if you pay attention to the
science
you can zero in on the fact that you
have very little control over sort of
subjective well-being
once you're out of poverty getting out
of poverty
big big difference okay so no political
status quo
argument here but one shot of that right
no there's not
much you can do to move that very much
you want to cultivate some skills and
some confidence
you want to have a sense of being in
control of your own life
that's important after that though what
really matters what is very malleable to
you
and what's really important in the
having of children and in getting old
is the fact that meaning in life is much
more manageable
much more malleable so don't think of
your pleasure as a
fixed sum it's not a zero-sum game
meaning in life can be continually
enhanced
developed cultivated what cultivates it
philia sophia the communal love
of wisdom that is one of the best forums
in which we can continue to enhance
meaning in life
even as we are losing power and fame
and physical health
and what our imagination teaches us is
if we die
surrounded by our philosophical
companions
we will die in a way that that is
that open-hearted
so is that sufficient for the
the profound questions of our mortality
no
but it is but is it powerful yes
we need to all practice whenever we're
imagining in a way that can drive us to
despair
we need to engage the epicurean
practices
of disciplining the imagination by using
the four-fold
cure and a version of it that is
enhanced by our best
cognitive science so that's what we can
take away
from the epicurean practice and what it
all
comes to them is the phylia sophia
the philosophical contemplative
contemplating wisdom
companionships
and we're going to turn to the work of
lahav on
friday how do we practice that okay so
jason's gonna help me now
and i apologize earlier uh for you know
that that little uh
the noise and then not being able to
find the eraser but jason's uh
behind the scenes he's looking he
couldn't find it i couldn't find it
so we're gonna move camera now and we're
going to do a short set
and we'll take some questions
okay
so welcome uh this is the orientation
that will allow me to see the tv screen
for the questions
i couldn't do that last time so
hopefully uh this isn't too
odd for you uh but we're gonna have a
sit now
so please um get yourself into a
comfortable position
set your phones on do not disturb uh we
will begin
with a chance a short chat and we'll go
into the silent sit and then we'll take
some questions
we'll begin when i say begin
again
one
home
in your silencer
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you've
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness
cognition character and communities
perhaps by reciting the five promises
to yourself
so let's try and take a couple of
questions for today
and jason's just pulling everything up
for us right now
and uh taekwon soho has a question here
i have been contemplating static
pleasure and realize i
only noticed active players could you
elaborate on mindfulness as an aide to
experiencing
static pleasure um so
that's what i was intending to do with
the um the the savoring experiences
um there is a place you can get to
i understand in one sense the savoring
when you're doing the walking and
transforming the world into a garden
that's an active it's you're doing
something um
but you come to him at least what
happens
is the mindfulness gets you to a place
where the joy
is not in any of the
textures or tones it's not right in that
the musicality of your intelligibility
um the joy drops to and that's the
intent the joy drops to
sorry i should be turning and looking at
you guys the joy adopts to
um the pleasure the pure pleasure of
being
and a way to think about that that is
like in
regular vipassana we're following the
flow of our breath and we're getting
into the flow
state that's very active but when we
when
when we pursue deep vipassana and drop
into the mindfulness
right uh that that mindfulness of the
space between our thoughts
the pure being of our mind in a similar
way
you're doing sort of like regular
something analogous to regular vipassana
when you're first
doing the savoring but then you can draw
to that silence underneath all the music
the the living silence the energetic
matrix of silence
that make amusing metaphors that makes
all the musicality
of intelligibility so beneath the
flowing pleasure
of the musicality of intelligibility
as you're walking and you're you're
experiencing the pure
pleasure of presencing you can draw on
this
right this moves a little bit beyond
epicureanism but with
mindfulness you can then think ah but i
can can i sense
that silence from which
the presence thing emerges and can i
come to
a kind of profound rest and peace
in that and
so the degree to which you can find
enjoyment
in the principle that regulates
presenting that generates it regulates
it
is a degree to which you can use a
profound kind of mindfulness
you can use deep vipassana a deep kind
of mindfulness
to access that profoundest kind of
anorexia
i hope that's helpful we'll take one
more question
uh deborah wagstaff observation i said
to my inner self i'm afraid that if i
let go i will come no one
and the voice i've never heard before
responds you will you will become no one
that's good thank you for sharing that
um deborah yeah that
that becoming no one again
there's a mystery there right because
think about it everything that you know
about yourself this is a distinction in
james
we'll talk about this when we get
further in everything that's my knee
oh that's what i am i'm john the teacher
uh john the father we
we've talked about this when we talked
about again
the deep you know the meditative
questioning right
or i'm john the tai chi player or this
is what john
looks like and you know this is arthur
dykman's point which he calls the
observing self
many traditions call this the whitman
self i'm looking
all those things that i'm looking at but
what i'm not looking at
ever is what's doing the looking
or language that i use right whenever i
step back and look at a frame
i'm not of the i can't see the frame
that i'm looking through
i can only see a previous frame that i
was looking through when i'm but i'm now
i'm looking at it
but i'm never seeing the deepest frame
through which i'm i'm looking you you
can't actually see
the seer and this is james's distinction
between the me
and the i like capital i right
and if you allow me a pun the eye can't
see itself
and i can't see itself your eye is
no thing no thingness it's no one
and if you can drop from
the multiplicity of the means
into the mystery of the eye
the no thingness the no one
then you are also dropping into again
that
place of profound peace
so i hope those were helpful questions
again there's a longer class
that's like for warren monday wednesdays
and fridays sorry about for a couple of
the technical glitches
uh but we're still adapting uh um i hope
this is getting better and
we are committed jason and ian mmr uh to
continually making it better
thank you very much everyone for joining
i want to thank jason he was behind the
scenes he was trying to tell me
where the market was i just couldn't get
it i'll find it and have it ready for
friday
um please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video to find links
to
awakening from the meeting crisis voices
with verbacy
please benefit uh how to uh sorry
please share this video with others whom
you think it might benefit
i happen to think it would help most
people but you know better
on the people that you interact with and
i certainly do and i don't want to be
presumptive
um because i'm sure please join the
discord
server to chat with others remember
we're not meeting here tomorrow
um but hopefully the discord server will
will hone that for everyone
you'll also find q a you'll find
movement practices evers
every day they do a second sits they do
longer sets um we're going to be housing
the philosophical
compensative companionship practice
there etc so please get involved with
the discord server
if you can please follow me on twitter
so that you'll be aware
of all the changes on all the streams
and any last-minute announcements that
need to be made
and please remember i will not see you
tomorrow but
continuity of practice is more important
than your quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to the standard of a
harsh perfectionism
but a virtuous friendship because there
is no enemy worse than your own mind and
body
there is no friend no ally true
companion on the path
better than your own mind and body you
lamps unto yourselves
and to each other i'll see you on friday
for our third dharma day
the dharma on philosophical
contemplative companionships
take good care everyone